Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we look at the effects
of animals on our health
and we start with the question,
do pet parents like me
(or pawrents) live longer?
Intense social connectivity
is a Blue Zone attribute
scrutinized for
its potential role
in supporting longevity.
Does slobbery
social contact count?
More than two-thirds
of U.S. households
include a pet (including mine!).
In an "awwww"-inspiring paper
published in the prestigious
journal Science entitled
"Oxytocin-gaze positive loop
and the coevolution
of human-dog bonds,"
researchers found that petting
or looking into the eyes
of a canine companion
leads to oxytocin release
in the brains of both
the humans and the dogs,
the same "love hormone" that
bonds breastfeeding mothers
to their infants.
I was reading about
the potential mechanisms
by which having
an animal companion
might improve survival
after a heart attack
when I ran across a passage
about a "profound"
cardiovascular response
when petting dogs or horses.
"This response
usually takes the form
of a significant reduction
in the heart rate
and blood pressure."
I could totally see that.
But then the next sentence
made me do a double take:
"Unfortunately,
we have no information
about
the physiological responses
of the person
doing the petting."
Oh, so they were talking
about the heart rate
and blood pressure
of the animals!
To my surprise,
studies of the effects
of companion animals
on human health have,
as one review put it,
produced a "mishmash
of conflicting results."
But a meta-analysis of studies
involving more than
three million people
followed for an average
of a decade
found that
canine companionship,
for example,
was associated with
a 24 percent reduction
in the risk
of premature death.
The authors suggested
that enhanced survival
may be a result
of increased physical activity
from walking the dog.
That could also help explain
why pet ownership
has been associated
with a lower risk of frailty.
Of course, this too
could be reverse causation,
where people
who are already active
are more likely to get a dog
in the first place,
but the greater issue
may be confounding factors.
Pet owners tend to be
younger, wealthier,
more educated,
and more married.
Sadly, when these types
of elements
are taken into account,
the significant mortality risk
reduction disappears.
The same appears to be true
for pet ownership in general.
The higher survival rate
becomes
statistically insignificant
once confounding factors,
like socioeconomic factors,
are taken into account.
When it comes specifically
to cats,
confounding can work
in the opposite direction.
Given evidence
that social support
may help with survival
after a heart attack,
a number of studies
have been undertaken
to see if pet ownership
can help.
One study found
that cat owners
had a significantly
greater risk of death.
This may be
because they appear
to not only be more likely
to be sedentary
than people with dogs,
who may be going on more walks,
but cat owners
may also be more sedentary
than people
without any pets at all.
Given the pitfalls
of trying to impute
cause-and-effect
from observational studies,
I was so excited to see
a randomized controlled trial
that actually put pet ownership
to the test.
Don't get your hopes
up too much, though.
The title was,
"Effect of Pet Insects
on the Psychological Health
of Community-Dwelling
Elderly People:
A Single-Blinded, Randomized,
Controlled Trial."
The "pets" were crickets.
But compared to
the control group,
older individuals
(average age 72)
randomized to take care
of crickets
experienced a significantly
greater improvement
in depression,
cognitive status,
and mental quality of life.
So, maybe there's hope
for Fido yet.
Most studies on pets
and human health
are snapshot-in-time studies
where it's impossible to know
which came first,
but longitudinal studies
over time have shown
that dog walkers
are indeed more likely
to achieve
recommended activity levels.
Sadly, only a minority--
only about a third--
of older dog owners
were found to even walk
their dogs three times a week.
To maximize the benefits
for pooch and person alike,
here's wise advice
from a medical journal article
published in 1925:
"The best prescription
to be written for a walk
is to take a dog..."
Finally today,
we look at how sharing your
home with a cat or dog
may decrease the risk of
infectious diseases in children—
including ear infections, respiratory
illnesses, and gastroenteritis.
To my surprise,
“studies of the effects of pets on human
health and well-being have [evidently]
produced a mishmash
of conflicting results.”
Some studies show pets
lower your blood pressure—
in fact, in some cases,
more than even drugs do.
But, other studies found no effect,
or even that pet owners
have higher blood pressure.
Does having a pet increase
your survival after a heart attack,
or decrease your survival
after a heart attack?
One area where there’s a bit more
consistency is children’s health.
The presence of furry pets in the home
appears to cut the odds
of acute respiratory illnesses in half,
and may even decrease the risk
of getting the common cold.
But, which pets work better?
Cats like my Charlotte, Emily,
and Ralph, or dogs like my Lilly?
Published recently in the official journal
of the American Academy of Pediatrics:
“Respiratory Tract Illnesses
During the First Year of Life:
Effect of Dog and Cat Contacts.”
“[T]he first study that has
evaluated the significance
of pet contacts during childhood
for the development of respiratory tract
[symptoms and] infections,”
including ear infections.
They found “dog and cat contacts during
early infancy may be associated with
less [illness] in general…and…
may have a protective effect
on respiratory tract
symptoms and infections.”
But as to which is better,
“In comparisons between
cat and dog contacts,
dog contacts showed
a more significant protective role
on respiratory infectious disease…”
“[C]hildren having a dog at home
were significantly healthier,
had less frequent
[ear infections],
and tended to need fewer courses
of antibiotics during the study period
than children without dog contacts.”
“Cat ownership seemed to also
have an overall protective effect,
although weaker than dog ownership,
on the infectious health of infants.”
Though, when it comes to protecting
children from tummy aches,
both cats and dogs appeared
equally effective in reducing
the risks of gastroenteritis.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.